This video is sponsored by the
all-in-one website builder, Odoo. Use my
link in the description to get started
for free.
Prominent American writer Mark Twain
[music] was born on November 30th, 1835.
On that same day, a comet known as
Halley's Comet had just recently passed
its closest point to the Sun on its
orbital path, becoming perceptible from
Earth to the naked eye for the first
time [music] in roughly 75 years. Known
as a short-period comet, this occurrence
happens once every 75 years or so.
>> [music]
>> And so, 75 years later, the comet made
its next visible appearance.
On the day after it was at its closest
point to the Sun on its departure away
from Earth, April 21st, 1910, Mark Twain
died of a heart attack.
The same day he was born and the same
day he died occurred alongside the
comet's rare proximity to Earth. Almost
as if their journeys were aligned,
synchronized.
Even more eerily, Twain spoke of having
a fascination and affinity with the
comet throughout his life.
The year prior to his death, he even
wrote, "I came in with Halley's Comet in
1835. It's coming again next year, and I
expect to [music] go out with it.
It would be a great disappointment to my
life if I don't. The Almighty has said,
no doubt, 'Now, here are these two
unaccountable freaks. They came in
together. They must go out together.'"
Of course, coincidences happen every
day, including ones that appear as
extreme or bizarre as Twain and Halley's
Comet. Most of the time, they're merely
modest moments of unlikely odds
>> [music]
>> that we quickly move on from. But other
times, they can be so strange and
unlikely, so extreme and specific, it
can make us question the very nature of
reality. It can almost feel as if
something else is at play.
We might wonder if coincidence is even
the right word.
Renowned 20th-century psychologist Carl
Jung wondered [music] the same thing.
For him, in certain cases, coincidence
was perhaps not the right word. [music]
Jung is one of the most influential and
esteemed psychologists in history.
>> [music]
>> His insights and theories have provided
new models and understandings of the
mind and the self. From his theories
about the unconscious mind, to dreams,
to symbols, [music] to archetypes, and
to a shared collective unconscious.
Among his many profound insights and
ideas, he had a very unusual theory
about apparent meaningful coincidences,
a theory he coined synchronicity.
Synchronicity is perhaps one of the most
controversial and misused terms across
psychology, philosophy, and
spirituality. Often being exploited and
contorted to fit various belief systems
and schools of thought, far removed from
its origins. In properly understood
terms, it's still highly questionable,
but far more robust than it's often
[music] presented.
In the book The Interpretation of Nature
and the Psyche, written by Jung and his
collaborator Wolfgang Pauli, a Nobel
Prize winning physicist who helped
pioneer quantum mechanics, Jung provides
a comprehensive overview of his theory
of synchronicity.
With a deep understanding of psychology
and vast experience in psychoanalysis,
Jung was especially prone to both
encounter and be interested in apparent
alignments between mind and external
reality.
With his theory of synchronicity, he
sought to make sense of these
occurrences, absurd-seeming,
odds-defying, meaningful coincidences.
Jung defined synchronicity as the
following: The simultaneous occurrence
of a certain psychic state with one or
more external events which appear as
meaningful parallels to the momentary
subjective state.
In other words, for an instance to be a
synchronicity, it can't merely be a
coincidence. It must include four
central qualities. First, [music]
it must be at least two separate events
where one is internal, like a dream,
thought, or feeling, and the other is
external. Second, [music]
there must be an a-causal connection
between the events. That is, they don't
directly cause or affect the other.
>> [music]
>> Third, the events must be experienced as
meaningfully related. And fourth, the
events must occur in close temporal
proximity. [music]
Being meaningful is essential both in
symbol and in time.
Meaningful, according to Jung here,
>> [music]
>> is when the internal event has a direct
or symbolic parallel with external
reality, and the perceived alignment
elicits a sense of importance.
To help clarify the distinction between
coincidence and synchronicity, Jung
writes, [music]
"Today is Friday. We have fish for
lunch. Somebody happens to mention in
the custom of making an April fish of
someone. That same morning, I made a
note of an inscription which read, 'The
man is completely a fish from the middle
downwards.'
>> [music]
>> In the afternoon, a former patient of
mine, whom I had not seen for months,
showed me some extremely impressive
pictures of fish which he had painted in
the meantime.
In the evening, I was shown a piece of
embroidery with fish-like sea monsters
in it.
On the morning of April 2nd, another
patient, whom I had not seen for many
years, told me a dream in which he stood
on the shore of a lake and saw a large
fish that swam straight towards her and
landed at her feet.
>> [music]
>> I was at this time engaged on a study of
the fish symbol in history.
Only one of the persons mentioned here
knew anything about it.
The suspicion that this must be a case
of meaningful coincidence, that is, an
a-causal connection, is very natural.
I must own that this run of events made
a considerable impression on me. It
seemed to me to have a certain numinous
quality.
In such circumstances, we are inclined
to say, 'That cannot be mere chance,'
without knowing what exactly we are
saying.
The strength of an impression, however,
proves nothing against the fortuitous
coincidence of all these fishes. [music]
One must remember that fish on Friday is
the usual thing, and on April 1st, one
might very easily think of the April
fish.
Fishes frequently occur as symbols of
unconscious contents, so there is no
possible justification for seeing in
this anything but a chance grouping."
Alternatively, an example of
synchronicity for Jung includes the
following experience he had while
treating one of his female patients who
was struggling to overcome
hyperrationalism and
overintellectualization.
>> [music]
>> In his office during a session, the
woman described to him a dream she had
the previous night about a piece of
jewelry in the form of a golden scarab
beetle.
As the woman described the dream, Jung
began to hear tapping on the window
behind him. When he turned around, he
found a scarab-like beetle trying to get
[music] inside. An unusual behavior for
the species in those conditions.
Jung opened the window, caught the
beetle out of the air, and then handed
it to the woman saying, "Here's your
beetle."
Notably, this experience meaningfully
altered the woman's perspective,
cracking the surface of her hardened
intellectualism, and allowing in a
softer sense of self and the world.
Unlike in the prior fish sequence, in
this case, the alignment happens in
close proximity in time, and there's an
apparent a causal connection between an
internal event, the woman's dreams,
thoughts, and statements, and the
external event, the sudden appearance
and unusual behavior of the beetle.
Jung writes,
"Should proof be forthcoming, however,
it would prove at the same time that
there are genuinely non-causal
combinations of events, for whose
explanation we should have to postulate
a factor incommensurable with causality.
We should then have to assume that
events in general are related to one
another on the one hand as causal
chains, [music]
and on the other hand by a kind of
meaningful cross connection."
For Jung, this kind of coincidence
involves such statistical absurdity and
symbolic meaning that the more likely
explanation is something deeper and
metaphysical. [music]
For him, they aren't merely signs of
something specific to the individual
experiencing them, but also signs of an
underlying nature of reality.
He writes,
"Synchronistic phenomena prove the
simultaneous occurrence of meaningful
equivalences and heterogeneous, causally
unrelated processes.
In other words, they prove that a
content perceived by an observer can, at
the same time, be represented by an
outside event without any causal
connection.
From this it follows either that the
psyche cannot be localized in space or
that space is relative to the psyche.
I do not need to emphasize that the
verification of these findings must have
far-reaching consequences.
Jung takes this rather giant leap based
on several other theories and premises
he establishes. Crucially, he believed
that the mind and reality are
fundamentally intertwined. He speculated
that matter and psyche flower from the
same stem, which he referred to as unus
mundus or one world, an underlying
unified substrate of the universe.
Synchronicity is made possible by this
because both the conscious observer and
an external event are connected by and
stemming [music] from the same source,
functioning by the same order, and
paralleling in consistent expressions. A
synchronicity is a moment in which this
connection or underlying order is
revealed.
With this, Jung is effectively departing
from a materialist physicalist view of
reality and consciousness.
Here, the fundamental nature of the
universe becomes a single unified whole.
Time becomes an illusion at the
foundations of the psyche and reality.
The unconscious mind becomes unbounded
and eternal. Reality is not matter over
mind or mind over matter, but mind and
matter as one. [music]
In doing this, Jung effectively arrives
at a novel version of a long-standing
philosophical and spiritual idea, one
that has transcended history and
geography. Similar notions of a unified
order of reality have echoes spanning
back to the voices of Heraclitus and the
Stoics with their idea of the logos,
Taoism's notion of the Tao, Hinduism's
Brahman, Arthur Schopenhauer's concept
of the will, along with many others.
Jung himself writes,
"If this is nothing less than a
restoration of the original state of the
cosmos and the divine unconsciousness of
the world, we can understand the
extraordinary fascination emanating
[music] from this mystery.
It is the Western equivalent of the
fundamental principle of classic Chinese
[music] philosophy, namely the union of
yang and yin in Tao, and at the same
time a premonition of that third thing,
which, on the basis of psychological
experience, I have called synchronicity.
Of course, with all these theories,
there's much that one is left to wonder
about and question. In terms of
synchronicity specifically, can things
truly be acausally linked? Can two or
more events be directly related to and
affecting of each other without any
tangible connection?
Moreover, how can we ever know?
Beyond that, what is this one world from
which everything stems?
Why are there specific archetypes and
symbols and orders associated with it?
And why only those kinds? Who decides
what's symbolic and meaningful?
Ultimately, we are so good at creating
meaning, we become really bad at
discerning truth.
We see meaning everywhere because we
create it with each perception, each
breath,
>> [music]
>> each step, each thought.
And perhaps, with billions of people,
trillions of thoughts, trillions of
actions, and trillions of moments, the
odds that two things that are seemingly
the same happen in alignment in time and
space between the inner and outer
domains
>> [music]
>> is what one would actually come to
expect.
Perhaps not.
A theory like synchronicity, as well as
its foundations and counterparts, are
unfalsifiable. They cannot be proven
false or tested against evidence. They
exist less in the realm of science and
more in that of the supernatural.
Researcher and author Roderick Main
writes in the introduction of the book
Jung on Synchronicity and the
Paranormal,
"The culmination of Jung's lifelong
engagement with the paranormal is his
theory of synchronicity."
The problem with knowing what is and
isn't supernatural [music]
is found in the fact that we simply
don't fully know what is natural.
To define something as supernatural
requires having a sufficient
understanding of what is, which we do
not.
We do not and likely will not know how
this universe and reality work.
No matter how deep we dig, we always hit
the bedrock of our ignorance and
fallibility.
We worship science and materialism as a
sort of salvation, a life raft made of
information designed to carry us into
the heavens of certainty.
Though this craft is undeniably
impressive, no matter how far we travel
in it, we will never escape ourselves.
Regardless of any underlying truth to
synchronicity, it is an extremely
fascinating idea that brings up
important questions about the
relationship between mind and reality,
between ontology and phenomenology,
between meaning and coincidence,
randomness and order. It compels us to
consider radical possibilities for what
existence is made of and how we
integrate with it. It reminds us that
there is something inherently other
about everything, something beyond our
comprehension that we participate in
without understanding, like an infinite
game of hide and seek where the hider is
also the seeker, but we haven't looked
enough places to discover this yet.
One of the easiest ways to dismiss an
idea is to say, "It's just a
coincidence."
But if everything that happens is merely
a coincidence, one is still left to
wonder,
why are coincidences happening?
Why
>> [music]
>> is anything happening?
Regardless of what reality is
fundamentally made of, with each of our
choices and actions, we clearly affect
it.
>> [music]
>> Our world is partly contingent on what
we do, share, express, and pursue. And
this video's sponsor, Odoo, allows you
to more easily take control of and
change your reality.
>> [music]
>> In the past, building a website or
managing a business was extremely
complex, overwhelming, and often
required multiple kinds of expertise.
Now, however, [music] with Odoo,
building and managing a website is
essentially a plug-and-play process,
[music] both streamlined and creatively
inspiring, and free.
Almost like a kind of digital creative
alchemy, with Odoo, you simply answer a
few prompts to find your vision and
goals, choose the look and feel you
want, and a working first version of
your website is forged [music] into
existence. From there, you can easily
drag and drop dynamic elements and
features until you have exactly what you
envisioned, bringing your internal world
into alignment with the external.
[music]
Whether you find your meaning in
artistic pursuits, a business, a social
cause, or all the above, Odoo helps make
it real.
>> [music]
>> And once your website is out in the
world and your project or business is
growing, Odoo allows you to manage
everything within the same integrated
platform, from inventory to goals to
accounting [music] and more.
With your first app free, unlimited
hosting and support, and a free custom
domain name for the first year, Odoo
makes everything simple, flexible, and
accessible. Get started for free by
using my link [music] in the
description.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general, and see
you next video.